ok this is a recorded interview today is
Monday februari 22nd in South 540 p.m.
for organic news on awake radio with a
CIA torture whistleblower John Kiriakou
and we're going to interview you a few
times before John thank you so much
awake radio is having a bit of technical
difficulties so I'm just recording
interviews and then they're gonna play
them so thank you for joining me John
Kerry I'm sure it's always it's always
great to be on this on the show thank
you very much for inviting me um we you
know we just had like a pretty lengthy
discussion before I started recording
and so you know whistle blowing and
standing up for what's right doesn't
really seem to be paying off much much
in this free country that we call
America is what we've concluded from
everything that we just talked about but
um we're going to discuss yesterday's
Washington Post article on geoffrey
sterling who is currently serving a
three and a half year sentence in a
prison in Englewood Colorado he was he
went in June of 2015 and will not get
out until 2018 and he has been convicted
of leaking information about a Russian
scientist trying to give faulty nuclear
plans on to screw up the Iranian nuclear
weapons program to James reisen of the
New York Times that's rude but he um it
was it was after geoffrey sterling was
already fired from the CIA because he
filed a lawsuit because he felt
discriminated against while working for
the CIA for almost ten years
approximate right yeah and Jeffrey tells
a very pointed story about that
experience he is fluent in Farsi he's an
expert on Iran and he was hired to be a
case officer an operations officer
that's a field officer field agent
working against the Iranians and so he
was assigned to go I think he said it
was to Germany and then right before he
was to leave his boss pulled him aside
and said we decided not to send you to
Germany because we think that a big
black guy speaking Farsi would would
stick out and he said when did you
realize I was black but they ended up
assigning him to a country somewhere in
Africa well the officer who was going to
go to Germany and replace if Jeffrey
ended up resigning and so they came back
and told Jeffrey we decided to send you
to Germany instead well he had already
sent off his all of his belongings to
Africa no I don't want to go to Germany
now I'm gonna go to Africa instead and
they said no you're gonna go to Germany
and if you don't want to go to journey
then you could just resign or you can be
fired so he resigned and filed a racial
discrimination suit which was
well-founded saying that he was
discriminated against initially because
he was black and they wouldn't send him
to germany in the first place um the CIA
did not argue the merits of that case
they went to the judge and they said
they that they wanted the case to be
dismissed with prejudice because the
only way for the agency to defend itself
was to expose classified information and
that's nonsense that's the national
security defense and that's what they
use all the time to protect themselves
so the judge it's the Eastern District
of Virginia it's the Espionage board
they do anything the CIA tells them to
do the judge
miss Jeffries case with prejudice well
James rising a two-time Pulitzer
prize-winning journalist with the New
York Times was covering for The Times
Jeffries racial discrimination suit so
because he was covering the case he
ingests he had end up a Jeffrey spoke
something like 52 times over the course
of several years in the meantime risin
came out with a book called bush at war
and one of the chapters in that book
details a botched case where the CIA
tried to recruit a Russian nuclear
scientist to get him to pass flawed
nuclear plans to the Iranian state of
war Dez dated war that's right no was it
state of war would work it said in the
article it was called state of being of
war then that's what it was so um when
the book was published the CIA just was
apoplectic they said that the whole
operation was classified at the top
secret level and um oh it must have been
Geoffrey who gave it to him right
because Jeffrey's district disgruntled
well listen i had had many private
conversations with geoffrey sterling and
he looked me in the eye and he told me I
was not rise ins source now listen again
Rison was a two-time Pulitzer
prize-winning journalist no New York
Times journalist would write an article
let alone a book using one source reisen
generally has dozens of sources but the
agency decided to go after Jeffrey but
they just they go after him because they
just decided that it was him like where
was the evidence and the facts you know
what I'm not even sure that they did
really decide that it was him I think
that they decided that they were going
to teach him a lesson right he had sued
them he had spoken to the press and by
god they were going to silence this guy
so it becomes like a moat you know
emotional and purse
rather than anything facts you're right
it's always personal and the goal and I
said just the financial press club the
other day when we did the the event for
Jeffrey with his wife Holly the goal is
not just to prosecute the goal is to
ruin the person personally
professionally financially to separate
him from his friends and his relatives
and to frighten other would-be
whistleblowers so that nobody talks that
the secrets are kept and that's what
happened to Jeffrey um again before I
started the recording I just I brought
up the the case of the guy I'm sorry
again I just like his name just keeps
escaping me who they held in solitary
confinement for 43 years right um in
Illinois sorry and um we Louisiana and
again that that case was purely personal
absolutely and most of these egregious
cases are indeed personal there's no
justice at all no you know there was a
guy in prison with me I never learned
his name but I'd see him on the track
every every every day and so in the
summer time he would take off his shirt
and he had this this monumental tattoo
on his back that made me laugh the first
time I saw but it made me think
afterwards and I thought you know
there's really something to this tattoo
it was a tattoo of Lady Justice and
she's holding her scales and she has her
blindfold on but she is laying on the
ground with with her right arm up as if
to protect herself and the owner of the
tattoo the guy who's back the tattoo is
on is standing above her pointing a 45
out of it and he says take that
and I laughed the first time I saw it it
was very clever and it is your ornate
but I said you know what there's a lot
to this because there's no justice in
the
system not when we have people in
solitary confinement for 43 years not
only have people in adx supermax who
have not seen another human being in
eight years as the New York Times
Magazine outlined you know not when we
have mandatory minimum sentences for for
minor drug offenses that land people in
prison in many cases for for you know
the majority of their lives that's not
justice and this is what happened to
geoffrey sterling there there's no
justice for geoffrey sterling everything
is a business yeah um and so the case of
geoffrey sterling you know it signified
obama's crackdown on um I wrote
truth-tellers but the article says uses
the word leakers uh yeah you know this
is a problem with the mainstream media
it's not monolithic um but but many
major outlets still refer to all of us
to to Jeffrey to Tom Drake jesselyn
Radack and to me as as leakers rather
than whistleblowers now the New York
Times calls us whistleblowers CNN calls
us whistleblowers but the Washington
Post and Politico for example call us
leakers the LA Times The Boston Globe
called us whistleblowers but MSNBC cause
us leakers Fox calls us traitors haha so
you know there's really no you get no
relief from most outlets in the
mainstream media and unless more people
like on the inside you know do what u
geoffrey sterling and and others like
Chelsea Manning and Edward Snowden have
done the few people who do are always
going to be seen as you know the
troublemakers yes always always um okay
I'm you know we don't have like you
don't have a lot of time we have like
ten minutes
so it says in the article geoffrey
sterling is tutoring other inmates um
he's finishing his memoir written by
hand because he can't there's he has to
mail it to his wife to type it yeah yeah
I wrote two books by hand and you know I
sent them out to my wife and typed him
when I got home but I'm talking about
you know ninety four thousand words that
I wrote by hand and that's exactly what
Jeffrey's doing too you're only allowed
to have a pen and some paper you
certainly have no access to a computer
um you know he holds his head high but
he does admit to feeling low some days
yeah you know this is another thing to
cat is the role of depression yeah in
our prison something like eighty percent
of prisoners at least in the federal
system take some form of antidepressant
there's there's no hope for most these
guys this is something that I asked
Jeffrey's wife Holly to to pass back to
him I said I know that it feels he has
three and a half years and I know it
feels like 30 years I know because I've
been there myself but it really isn't a
very long period of time once you get
past that first year with halfway house
and good behavior time off and house
arrest I said three and a half years is
really about two years once you finish
that first year you can actually start
counting down to release I think he's
finally figured that out but now he's
even more worried about what kind of
work you know a guy who's been convicted
of seven counts of espionage can hope to
get to support his family you know like
that's that's it just it to when you're
out of prison you're not exactly free no
no and we he's got I think it's two
years of federal probation when he's
when he's done but you know like all the
rest of us who've been involved in
national security cases he's lost his
federal pension he lost the right to
vote um he's an attorney and he's been
disbarred because of his because of his
conviction so you know where does he
work he is he gonna work at Target or at
McDonald's or in starbucks see that is
he's lucky seems look you will they yeah
I mean that's what I'm just going to say
it I mean that's what this system wants
to do it wants to just reduce everyone
choose that's what I mean about your not
necessarily even free like when you're
out here because there's so many people
out here just you know who can't who
don't have really good paying jobs and
are you know stuck oh you know working I
mean lately they don't even have a
decent um in a wage to pay people yeah
that's right that's right you know Holly
told me that Jeffrey's making something
like sixteen dollars a month um no it
was less than that it would it was no
yeah he makes fifty cents a day tutoring
wow so so he makes two and a half bucks
a week ten bucks a month so um I said
you know what I made a dollar ate a
month so if he's making ten bucks a
month he's doing pretty darn low for
himself Wow yeah so he is inmate 3833
eight dash 0 for 4 yes and he's taking
classes in checking and savings account
so that when he gets some released
that's going to help him to get released
to a halfway house well know you'll get
released to a halfway house regardless
of what he does just because it's his
right to a halfway house well it ought
to be his rape
yes I got no halfway house time at all
because I was writing blogs from prison
about problems in prison and so I did
every single day of my sentence I didn't
get any relief at all um but he's you
know he's really doing it the way you're
supposed to do it he's keeping his head
down he's minding his own business he's
trying to help other inmates fight by
teaching a GED prep class um I told him
legally he's allowed to have up to 12
months of halfway house time and what
that really means is two weeks and then
they just send you home and the rest of
it converts into house arrest I said
realistically you're probably going to
get six months um but six months plus
three months of house arrest that's nine
months getting out nine months early and
going home plus you're a good time which
is fifteen percent of your total time
which is another six and a half months
you know that's fifteen and a half
months off of a 42-month sentence so
it's barely over two years I said you
can do that you can do two years I mean
if he if he has the support out here
that will definitely help them too
that's right and that's what he needs he
needs the support of the community the
guys in whistleblower he's not a
criminal he's not a leaker no matter
what the CIA wants you to believe no
matter what the Justice Department wants
you to believe the guy is the victim
here geoffrey sterling is the victim
right you know it's just like it amazes
me how automatically like so many people
just side with the system or the
official story always against you know
the one single person and it doesn't
ever enter people's mind or maybe it's
just too challenging for people to ever
think that it's the system who is the
guilty party right or the people you
know working in the system like in the
case of you know again
is mr Wood Wood foxwood Fox who they
just let out of solitary confinement for
43 years and I mean he was basically
held without any evidence or fax I mean
it literally became personal well it was
personal yeah on the part of the judge
he have somebody back 43 years and you
know I'm amazed to and how the guy at
least seems to be he seems to have his
mental faculties how person cannot go
completely insane after 40 years in
solitary confinement and i will add that
the United Nations has described
solitary confinement as its practiced in
the United States as a form of torture
solutely so this guy has been tortured
for 43 years and he seems to hold no
bitterness he know people who did this
thing well that's because he's right
he's not in his right mind that that's
what I what I would think but he is he
is filing a lawsuit though there is a
lawsuit um and also in the article on
Jeffrey that is in the Washington Post
yesterday it says that Rob um James
reisen of the New York Times could come
forward to exonerate geoffrey sterling
but he threw it an attorney he doesn't
give any common that's that's been a
tough issue I know rising personally and
horizon took this whole thing very very
badly too I know that I know that Norman
Solomon exposed faqs org who has been a
great and true friend to Jeffrey and and
great supporter has said that there are
no hard feelings and there's no ill will
it's true that risin could have gone on
the stand and he could have said
geoffrey sterling was not my source for
the book and he never did that what he
did was he refused to testify period now
mission was if he had gone up on onto
the stand and had said that Jeffrey
wasn't the source that would have opened
him up to follow on questions from the
prosecution and if he had refused to
answer those he could have been held in
contempt of court now some people would
argue that that's what a man would have
done men would have stood up and he
would have taken his lumps um reisen was
not sent to prison for contempt of court
but at the same time he didn't help
Jeffrey's cause in any way uh so um his
wife she's gonna stand by him and she's
a rock-solid supporter they have a very
strong and loving marriage and um you
know he's going to rely very much on her
when he gets home and he's liking have
her just like I was lucky to have my
wife so many whistleblowers don't have
that kind of support somebody
whistleblowers seat need the breakup of
their of their family while the rest of
their life is just crashing down around
them but neither Jeffrey nor I had to
deal with that ah so let me see yeah
right it's six o'clock okay John our
time is up oh it's great to speak with
you as always yeah I mean anything that
you need to share just let me know and
so exposed faqs org yes expose facts org
and they have something called the
whisper program that's the whistleblower
protection I forget what the R stands
for whistleblower protection and
something um but you know if you're
thinking of blowing the whistle on waste
fraud abuse or illegality or threats to
the public health or public safety
you're going to need an attorney and a
good one and that attorneys jessalyn
rate at at exposed to xorg thank you so
much john kerry aku great to speak with
you you too boy ok good night
I'm